Okay בוקר טוב boker tov everybody. We today's דף, daf,
today's דף daf is דף ט, daf tet, and we pick up
at the bottom of ח עמוד
ב. chet amud bet. גמרא Gemara says like this, we switched from
the importance of rain and the things that bring rain and the
things that cause rain to cease to some comments of sometimes even
when it rains and it's important for necessary for the crops or
whatever could still be a סימן קללה. siman klala. And the point
I was making there was not that it is a קללה, klala,
but a סימן קללה siman klala and again going to the issue
of the symbolism and the religious significance right into the rain. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
the following.
Okay,
we'll pick up from that again. אמר רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak,
which is about four lines before the lines get wide on ח
עמוד ב, chet amud bet, middle of the line, five lines. אמר
רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak, אפילו שנים כשני אליהו, afilu shanim kishnei
Eliyahu, even if the years were like the years of אליהו, Eliyahu,
you know, terrible drought for many years, וירדו גשמים בערב שבתות, veyardu
geshamim be'erev Shabbatot, but if the rain fell on Friday, אינו אלא
סימן קללה. eino ela siman klala. And so that's a sign, what?
That is a sign of a curse. Right, שבת, Shabbat,
presumably, that's what רש"י Rashi explained. היינו דאמר רבא בר שילה קשי
יומא דמיטרא כיומא דדינא. Hainu de'amar Rava bar Shila kashi yoma de'mitra
ke'yoma de'dina. A day of rain can sometimes be as difficult, let's
say as inconvenient, as the marketplace day, the day of the that
the courts are sitting in terms of the the crowds and the
you know ever try to get a taxi in the rain? So
you know, there are there are inconveniences that are created by the
rain. So again, that's quite funny, you're going years of drought and
you're complaining that it's raining on a Friday because you have to
go outdoors and prepare for שבת. Shabbat. But again, the point being
not that it is a קללה, klala, but the fact that it
that when it did rain, it rained דווקא davka on a Friday,
that is a סימן קללה. siman klala. So again, it's a question
about the religious meaning we read and sort of seeing rain as
a way in which to sort of indicates how God is communicating
to us. Any interest into your thoughts there? No, religiously troubled. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר מימר אילו לא צריך לבריתא
בעינן רחמי ומבטלינן ליה. Amar Memar ilu lo tzarich lebriyata be'inan rachamei
u'mevatlinan leh.
Now this seems like a more general complaint about rain. If it
weren't that rain was so necessary, not about a סימן קללה, siman
klala, but just about a question again of inconvenience, if it weren't
that rain were so necessary for our survival, you know, it was
necessary for for the world, I would just pray that there should
never be rain. So here's somebody who did not like, you know,
all he could talk about when it rained was that how it
was making his life difficult. So again, quite fascinating this discordant voice
amongst all of this discussion. ואמר רבי יצחק, V'amar Rabbi Yitzchak, and
said רבי יצחק, Rabbi Yitzchak, שמש בשבת צדקה לעניים. shemesh b'Shabbat tzedaka
le'aniyim.
If there's if it's a sun on שבת, Shabbat, then that's a
kindness or righteousness to the poor. שנאמר וזרחה לכם יראי שמי שמש
צדקה ומרפא. Shene'emar vezarcha lachem yirei shemi shemesh tzedaka u'marpe.
And it will shine for you those that fear My name, the
sun of righteousness and it and its healing and it will be
healing. So again, not exactly clear what it means לעניים, le'aniyim, maybe
the עניים aniyim do not have a field and they don't have
to worry about the rain. So for them, you know, this is
like a like a, you know, a flip side of the coin
of what was said before. They can just appreciate the fact that
it's a nice sunny day and they don't have to go to
work on שבת, Shabbat, so they lie out and they sun themselves
and they relax and it's very lovely.
And walk over to
a meal, by the way.
Oh, walk over to maybe, yes. Eat outside on שבת, Shabbat, they
go over and get.
Yeah, that's what Michael just said, right? Right, that's what Michael just
suggested, that it lets them other people are in a better mood,
they want to share their food.
Okay. ואמר רבי יצחק. V'amar Rabbi Yitzchak. And said רבי יצחק. Rabbi
Yitzchak. אין ברכה מצויה אלא בדבר הסמוי מן
העין. Ein beracha metzuya ela bedavar hasamui min ha'ayin. Famous line. Blessing
is only found by something hidden from the eye. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as
the verse says, יצו ה' אתך, Yitzav Hashem itcha, did I skip
a line? I did skip a line. Thank you. Thank you, thank
you, thank you. Okay, second medium line, I skipped a line.
ואמר רבי
יצחק. V'amar Rabbi Yitzchak. יום גשמים, Yom geshamim, so we're back to
גדול יום גשמים. Gadol yom geshamim. So before you say גדול יום
גשמים Gadol yom geshamim like מתן תורה, mattan Torah, you know, like
other types of like תחיית המתים, techiyat hametim, here's יום גדול יום
גשמים yom gadol yom geshamim not in terms of a metaphor and
a comparison, but in terms of the blessings that it brings with
it. Great is the day of rain, שאפילו פרוטה שבכיס מתברכת בו,
she'afilu peruta shebakis mitbarechet bo,
that even stuff that's not connected to rain, even the money in
your bank
account is blessed. So it's brings a fortune and success to all
endeavors, a day of rain. שנאמר מתברכת בו שנאמר, Shene'emar mitbarechet bo
shene'emar, לתת מטר ארצך בעתו ולברך את כל מעשה ידך. latet matar
artzecha be'ito u'levarech et kol ma'aseh yadecha.
So not only is the rain, but with the rain in general
comes a blessing to all of your endeavors. And again here's again
sort of seeing this issue that rain, I believe, sort of signifies
God's connection to the land, favor to the people, bringing blessing. So
if it's a if it's not just what it is, but it's
also a sign of blessing, then it brings with it other forms
of blessing as well, and all things are blessed.
If you're a farmer, this is literally
Well, it's literally true, yes, but his point is going beyond being
a farmer. His point is even if you got money in your
bank account, somehow it gets blessed. The stock market goes up when
it rains. That's what he's saying. Okay, so he's making a point
that it's not just the immediate sort of impact, you know, the
obvious impact of the rain. Okay. What? Investing on rainy days?
Yeah,
you could go ahead and see if there's any correspondence, there you
go, make a killing in the market if you find even a
little bit of a correspondence. Okay, anyway, so the Gemara says like
this: ואמר רבי יצחק, Ve’amar Rabbi Yitzchak, says Rabbi Yitzchak, אין הברכה
מצויה—now ein habracha metzuya this you see the connection again because talking
about the blessing of your wealth, so you know, even in non-obvious
or you know, not necessarily obviously causal ways—so says Rabbi Yitzchak, אין
הברכה מצויה אלא בדבר הסמוי מן העין. ein habracha metzuya ela bedavar
hasamui min ha’ayin. Bracha can only be, will only be found in
something hidden from the eye. שנאמר, Shene’emar, you know, this יצו ה׳
אתך את הברכה באסמיך. yetzav Hashem itcha et habracha be’asamecha.
God should command the blessing to you in your gathering, but באסמיך,
be’asamecha, play on words סמוי, samui, in that which is hidden. Like
that’s the whole idea of saying like קינאהורה, keina hora, you know,
when you mention, you know, you say something, you point out a,
you know, something about someone, so then you’re like, you know, something
good, I mean, it’s also that like that provokes jealousy and provokes
other people to give you an עין הרע, ayin hara, so you
want to say קינאהורה, keina hora, but the also point is is
that if you don’t publicize the thing and you allow it to
be beneath the surface, it allows it to be blessed. Once you’re
sort of identifying it and focusing on it, it’s harder for it
to increase because maybe therefore God’s, God’s activity would be more obvious.
You’re asking God to do a more obvious miracle if you want
something; if you count up all your money and you have, you
have a thousand dollars and next you go back and there’s two
thousand dollars, it’s an obvious miracle. If you don’t know how much
money you had and then you’re allowing the blessing to occur, you’re
allowing, you know, God to work in more hidden ways, seems to
be the idea. But let’s keep on reading a little bit. תנא
דבי רבי ישמעאל, Tana devei Rabbi Yishmael, אין הברכה מצויה אלא בדבר
שאין העין שולטת בו. ein habracha metzuya ela bedavar she'ein ha'ayin sholetet
bo. Seems to be the same point said in different words. Blessing
is only found by something that the eye does not, you know,
does not have dominion over. שנאמר, Shene’emar, יצו ה׳ אתך את הברכה
באסמיך. yetzav Hashem itcha et habracha be’asamecha. In your gathering. Same, seems
to be same pasuk, seems to be same point. תנו רבנן, Tanu
rabanan, and now we’re going to spell it out even more. הנכנס
למוד את גרנו. Hanichnas lamod et gorno. You’re going to measure your
granary. אומר, Omer, יהי רצון מלפניך ה׳ אלהינו שתשלח ברכה במעשה ידינו.
Yehi ratzon milfanecha Hashem Elokeinu shetishlach bracha bema’aseh yadeinu. God, please, you
know, give blessing to the, to the acts of our hands. התחיל
למוד, Hitchil lamod, אומר, omer, ברוך השולח ברכה בכרי הזה. Baruch hasholeach
bracha bakari hazeh. Blessed is the one who sends his blessing to
this mound of grain. מדד, Madad, now you’ve measured it, so all
this is before you know exactly how much you have. Now you
measure the grain and you know how much you have. ואחר כך
בירך, Ve’achar kach beirach, and then you make a blessing God should
send His blessing. הרי זו תפילת שוא. harei zu tefillat shav. That
is a prayer of
naught, a purposeless prayer. לפי שאין הברכה מצויה לא בדבר השקול ולא
בדבר המדוד ולא בדבר המנוי אלא בדבר הסמוי מן העין. Lefi she’ein
habracha metzuya lo bedavar hashakul velo bedavar hamadud velo bedavar hamanoi ela
bedavar hasamui min ha’ayin. If you know, not something weighed or measured
or counted, only something hidden from the eye. And again, this really
seems to be the idea like, you know, as far as you’re
concerned before you’ve measured it, you know, what’s going to happen, you
know, also is there going to be more grain than there was
before? And presumably that seems to be the point, that God could
allow a miracle to happen or something to happen if it’s not
obvious that God is, you know, is violating the laws of nature.
Until you don’t know about, while you don’t know about it, there
could be, God could effect some change. But once it’s measured and
you know exactly what you’re talking about, then you’re demanding from God
to change the laws of nature and that God is not going
to do. You know, it’s sort of like there’s a famous Gra
about this because there’s a mishna in, in Brachot about תפילת שוא.
tefillat shav. It says that somebody who hears let’s say something terrible
happened in the city and says oh I hope that didn’t happen
in my house, הרי זו תפילת שוא. harei zu tefillat shav. Like
you hear an ambulance and say oh I hope it’s not anybody
I know, you know, you pray, it’s a תפילת שוא tefillat shav
because whatever happened already happened. So the Vilna Gaon says
it’s not like God couldn’t change the past, it’s just that God
won’t. So you can sort of think about your science fiction, you
know, time travel questions about that. But anyway, but the point being
similar to I think this point, God can change, you know, can
create a miracle that violates nature, He could give you more grain
than you thought you had, but He won’t do it once, once
it’s obvious, like once it’s measured and you know what’s happening, then,
then it’s not going to happen.
So it can actually be reasons for two things, why it’s taboo
to count people because then it’s like
revealing and it ties into וידגו לרוב veyidgu larov so we don't
see fish, right.
Right, so that is
so it is true, so וידגו לרוב veyidgu larov like fish hidden
from the eyes and it ties into
the sense you actually get is is that you don't want to
quantify, by quantifying it you are, you know, you are sort of
by quantifying the blessing you're somehow minimizing the blessing, you know, and
it's better some things to last unquantified.
Okay. So anyway but I think again what's interesting about this, the
two statements of רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak tying into a ברכה, beracha,
is the sense that God's blessing works not only in natural ways.
When it rains, even the money in your bank account blesses, you
know, or at least if you don't know the bank account because
that's maybe that's already counted the exact amount. But it's not only
the natural impact of rain, God's blessing comes with the rain and
can act in ways that are not necessarily causal in a natural
sense, but you have to allow it to happen behind the scenes.
Yes.
It's funny because I would think that the argument goes the other
way. Mhm. The argument about rain being a blessing is like this
is a fundamental
impetus for the economy.
Ah, interesting. Oh that's interesting. You mean so if if if there's
better produce all around then it stimulates the economy in all in
all various ways.
Stimulates consumer demand, the macroeconomy.
Right, that's interesting.
It's good for everybody. And I would have thought that this this
collection of of statements from רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak is actually saying
that God works from the big strokes of history, the big strokes
of meteorology, and you might want to think that he's doing special
stuff for you and anybody who says that they see God's hand
being revealed to them, he doesn't buy it. He says it happens
in a silo when you're totally unaware. Right.
So you want to read him pushing the opposite. Yeah.
Total total rules of nature and the economy.
That's interesting. Okay יישר כוח, shkoyach, so a few a few פרוטות
prutos objective understood very in a very sort of natural terms, not
that... that's interesting. And then consistent with the idea that he's saying
don't claim supernatural involvement. That's not the way things happen, right. That's
nice. Okay. All right, thank you. All right, so now the גמרא
Gemara goes on, we have these little words קיבוץ גשמים צדקה פרנסה
Kibbutz Geshamim Tzedakah Parnassah but you'll see there's a סימן siman meaning
that's just a mnemonic for the next things that are going to
be stated. אמר רב יוחנן: Amar Rav Yochanan: גדול יום הגשמים כיום
קיבוץ גלויות. Gadol yom hageshamim k'yom kibbutz galuyot. So back to the
idea of how great is a day of the rain. So again
we had digressions in general what makes it rain, what stops it
from raining, the last גדול יום הגשמים gadol yom hageshamim was to
say about the ברכה beracha that comes with it, but now we're
back to our normal theme which is to create to talk about
some type of an analogy or a metaphor. So great is the
day of of rain like the day of the gathering of the
exiles. שנאמר: She'ne'emar: שובה השם את שביתנו כאפיקים בנגב. Shuva Hashem et
sheviteinu k'afikim baNegev. God return our captivity like the you know like
the rushing waters in the you know in the Negev. ואין אפיקים
אלא מטר V'ein afikim ela matar and אפיקים afikim is the rain
שנאמר: she'ne'emar: ויראו אפיקי ים vayera'u afikei yam and they saw the
the streams of the ocean. Now how does that stream mean rain?
ואמר רב יוחנן... V'amar Rav Yochanan... oh no, so that's it. So
it doesn't exactly say, but somehow it means I think רש״י Rashi
says here מוצאי
ים. motzai yam. Anyway somehow it means the rushing waters and therefore
here it's understood to mean the rushing... the rain. Although probably also
what it really means is that when it rains and it goes
into the ואדי, Wadi, it creates these you know these rushing streams
so the rain brings around the אפיקים. afikim.
And
a נחל nachal is dry.
Right, a נחל nachal is a ואדי Wadi and then
it becomes exactly. So it's funny the quotes from the פסוק pasuk
over there from ויראו אפיקי ים. vayera'u afikei yam. פשט Pshat of
the פסוקים psukim is like it's you know that's the whole idea
that the return of the captivity is all of a sudden like
you get a you know rain and you get a flash flood
you know because all the way the ואדי Wadi works it looks
like a funnel, like it funnels all of the water into you
know into the ואדי. Wadi. Okay.
He said a third, I was just... yeah he said a third
of an inch of
rain can cause a flood fifteen feet high. Really? Wow. Okay.
Okay, ואמר רב יוחנן, v'amar Rav Yochanan, says רב יוחנן: Rav Yochanan:
גדול יום הגשמים שאפילו גייסות פוסקות בו. Gadol yom hageshamim she'afilu gaysot
paskot bo. Great is the day of rain that even the troops
stop then, which maybe means they stop marching because it's raining but
also maybe means they take a break from going to war. שנאמר,
She'ne'emar, as the verse says: תלמיה רוה נחת גדודיה. tlameha ravvei nachat
gdudeha. You have you have sated its
furrows and the troops have rested. So the troops here meaning like
even the troops the army troops. It doesn't really literally mean...
it means like cause גדוד gdud you know as in the banks?
Probably. ואמר רב יוחנן: V'amar Rav Yochanan: אין הגשמים נעצרים. ein hageshamim
ne'etzarim. Okay, אין הגשמים נעצרים, ein hageshamim ne'etzarim, rain is only withheld,
back to why rain is withheld now, אלא בשביל פוסקי צדקה ברבים
ואין נותנים. ela bishvil poskei tzedakah barabbim v'ein notnim. So this is
an interesting thing to connect to and and here we really see
we'll see a direct metaphor. People that promise to give צדקה tzedakah
you know you know amongst in in public and then they don't
fulfill it. to their promise. שנאמר, shene'emar, as the verse says, נשיאים
ורוח וגשם אין. nesi'im veruach vegeshem ayin. So the, you know, it's
like the clouds and wind but no rain. איש מתהלל במתת שקר,
ish mithallel bematat shaker, and that's a person praising himself with false
gifts, with, you know, so therefore it's the same thing, there's a
lot of wind, you know, we hear all your words, we hear
all your promises but there's no rain that comes afterwards. The actual,
the actual תכלית, tachlis, you know, that what that we're longing for
and that we need doesn't follow all of the wind and all
of the promises. So, same type of, so that is exactly paralleled
by these promises of rain that don't materialize. ואמר רבי יוחנן ve'amar
Rabi Yochanan and says רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan מאי דכתיב, mai dichektiv,
what's meant by the verse, top of כ"ז עמוד א, kaf-zayin amud
aleph, עשר תעשר, aser te'aser, you should certainly take tithes. עשר בשביל
שתתעשר. aser bishvil shetit'asher. Take tithes in order that you shall become
rich. So here we are, you know, again going to this correspondence:
you do this and God responds that way. So, and we've discussed
already the issue of rain not coming because of the lack of
giving תרומות ומעשרות, terumot uma'asrot, the lack of sort of recognizing God's
hand, so therefore there's no rain. And we just saw a similar
correspondence here, you know, you promise to give others, you give others,
you know, that leads to the giving, God giving you the rain.
And here too now so taking rain out of the picture di,
or at least in, you know, we're not directly having it in
the picture, but if you give your מעשר ma'aser then you will
be recompensed, there will be a מידה כנגד מידה middah kineged middah
and you will become rich. So obviously a play on words here.
אשכחיה רבי יוחנן לינוקא דריש לקיש ashkenacho Rabi Yochanan leyanuka deReish Lakish
and רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan found the child of ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish and we will see two things in this story. Number one,
this was his nephew, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish was married to his
sister. And number two, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish was already dead as
we'll see a little bit later in the story. Anyway, so he
found ריש לקיש Reish Lakish's child and אמר ליה amar lei and
said to him, אימי לי פסוקיך, eimai li piskeicha, tell me the
פסוק pasuk that you're learning. אמר ליה עשר תעשר. amar lei aser
te'aser. I'm learning the פסוק עשר תעשר, pasuk aser te'aser, you should
take tithes. אמר ליה מאי עשר תעשר? amar lei mai aser te'aser?
Now it's a little bit unclear here because it has another אמר
ליה, amar lei, but it's clear from later that basically this child
said to רבי יוחנן, Rabi Yochanan, what does the פסוק pasuk mean?
Like you know, give me some insight into the פסוק. pasuk. I
understand so I understand אמר ליה עשר בשביל שתתעשר. amar lei aser
bishvil shetit'asher. Ah let me tell you a good פשט. pshat. Give
מעשר ma'aser in order that you should become rich. אמר ליה amar
lei so the child said to him, מנא לך, minallah,
how do you know? You know, that's a nice little דרש drash
but how do you know it works? אמר ליה זיל נסי, amar
lei zil nasei, give it a try. Go ahead, see what'll happen.
Do a test. אמר ליה ומי שרי לנסויי לקודשא בריך הוא? amar
lei umi shari lenasuyei leHakadosh Baruch Hu? Is it appropriate to test
God? וכתיב לא תנסו את ה, vechektiv lo tenasu et Hashem, do
not test God. So I'm gonna test God, I'm gonna give מעשר
ma'aser and see if it actually makes me rich? אמר ליה amar
lei said back to him, הכי אמר רבי אושעיא, hachi amar Rabi
Oshaya, this is what רבי אושעיא Rabi Oshaya says, חוץ מזו, chutz
mizo, this is the one thing that you're allowed to test God,
this is the exception, שנאמר shene'emar as the verse says, הביאו את
כל המעשר אל בית האוצר, havi'u et kol hama'aser el beit ha'otzar,
bring all of the tithes to the, you know, to the gathering
house to the storehouse, ויהי טרף בביתי viyehi teref beveiti and there
will be food in my house, ובחנוני נא בזאת, uvchanuni na bazot,
you may test me in this matter, אמר ה צבאות, amar Hashem
Tzeva'ot, אם לא אפתח לכם את ארובות השמים, im lo eftach lachem
et arubot hashamayim, if I will not open for you the, the
store, no yeah well no ארובה arubah is the the windows of
the heaven, והריקתי לכם ברכה עד בלי די, vaharicoti lachem bracha ad
bli dai, and I will pour down to you blessing without enough.
מאי עד בלי די mai ad bli dai
or without, you know, without limit. What does it mean עד בלי
די? ad bli dai? אמר אמי בר חמא אמר רב, amar Ami
bar Chama amar Rav, עד שיבלו שפתותיכם מלומר די. ad sheyivlu siftoteichem
milomar dai. Until, this is obviously a play בלה, balah, יבלו, yivlu,
בלי, bli, until your lips grow weary saying enough, enough, enough. There'll
be so much you'll, you know, you'll be weary saying that it's
enough and I'll still there'll be more blessing. So you're allowed to
test God, give your מעשר ma'aser and it'll all work out. אמר
ליה, amar lei, so this kid said back to רבי יוחנן, Rabi
Yochanan, his nephew, אי הוה מטי התם להאי פסוקא, i hava miti
hatam lehai pasuka, had I you know, you stopped me, I was
looking עשר תעשר, aser te'aser, I didn't get up yet to מלאכי,
Malachi, that was like two years later in my learning, but had
I got up to that פסוק, pasuk, אי הוה מטי להאי פסוקא
לא הוה צריכנא לכל הושעיה רבך. i hava miti lehai pasuka lo
hava tzrichna lechol hoshaya rabhach. I wouldn't have needed you or הושעיה
Oshaya your רבי. rabbi. I could've figured that out myself with the
פסוק. pasuk. I needed you to tell me a פסוק, pasuk, so
I didn't know the פסוק pasuk yet but it's no big חידוש.
chiddush. Okay anyway, so it wouldn't have been maybe a play of
עשר תעשר, aser te'aser, I wouldn't have sort of done the play
on words, but the פסוק pasuk is clear. It says bring the
מעשר ma'aser and I'll give you wealth. Now the interesting thing I
would mention here by the way is here's a פסוק pasuk that
explicitly says that I'll give you rain, right? Or it's implicit, maybe
not explicit, I'll open up ארובות השמים. arubot hashamayim. Now you know,
you could say like, you know, there's that one story right by
the נביא Navi where it says God opened the ארובות השמים arubot
hashamayim and like like the image of like I'm going to pour
grain down the window, not not rain. But still presumably opening up
the heavens and being blessed with grain means being blessed with rain.
And nevertheless this פסוק pasuk is not brought in into the explicit
discussion of like what brings rain. Like why does it say like
you know, מעשר ma'aser brings rain, you know, and test
to test that. So it's interesting how, again, I don't have an
explanation, but it's interesting how it's sort of taken as a standalone
point. Now interestingly about that is that this leads to—not this alone,
but you know, there's a whole custom that develops in the period
of the אשכנזי Ashkenazi ראשונים Rishonim about מעשר כספים, Maaser Kesafim, about
tithing your income,
which is not, you know, in any גמרא, Gemara, it's not in
the פסוקים, Pesukim, because, you know, there the technical halachic obligation is
only about the grain and is only in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
But of course once the economy shifts
from—that's true—but once the economy shifts from agriculture
to commerce and other types of things, you know, so where's the
whole concept of מעשר? Maaser? What does it all go to? So,
you know, so תוספות, Tosafot, if you take a look, תוספות Tosafot
quotes he quotes this in the name of the ספרי. Sifrei. It
is not in the ספרי Sifrei that we have. And when I
read it you tell me why what the indication is that this
is clearly a medieval דרשה. drasha. So look at the first line
of תוספות: Tosafot: עשר תעשר. Aser Teaser. הכי איתא בספרי: Hachi itta
besifrei: עשר תעשר את כל תבואת זרעך היוצא השדה שנה בשנה. Aser
teaser et kol tevuat zarchah hayotze hasadeh shanah beshanah. אין לי אלא
תבואת זרעך שחייב במעשר. Ein li ela tevuat zarchah shechayav bemaaser. ריבית
ופרקמטיא וכל שאר רווחין מנין? Ribbit uprakmatya vechol shear revachin minayin? How
about interest and business, commerce, and all other types of
income-generating activities? How do I know you have to give מעשר? Maaser?
תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar את כל, et kol, so not just מעשר,
maaser, את כל מעשר. et kol maaser. מה תלמוד לומר את תבואתך?
Ma talmud lomar et tevuatecha? מה
כל? Ma kol? לרבות ריבית ופרקמטיא וכל דבר שמרויח בו. Lerabot ribbit
uprakmatya vechol davar shemarviach bo. Okay, and then he goes on with
other types of
אגדתא aggadata talks about that if you don't give מעשר, Maaser, then
you'll only then, you know, you'll only get a tenth of what
you then the roles will reverse. Until now you took 90 percent
and you gave up 10 percent. If you don't give מעשר, Maaser,
then your stuff will only produce 10 percent of what it used
to do and God will take the other 90 percent, you know,
and all of the negative consequences of not giving מעשר Maaser and
the positive consequences of giving it. So one thing obviously that's been
important is by eliminating rain from the equation here, right, it becomes
more speaking about bottom line, you know, as opposed to again the
emphasis here which is so much about the rain and its religious
significance, it's sometimes a little bit difficult to give מעשר, Maaser, right?
10 percent's a lot, like I worked all this hard, I'm going
to give away 10 percent. So we focused right on the bottom
line: you give your 10 percent and this is a good investment,
you'll get rich, right? So that also like helps encourage the giving
of the מעשר Maaser and it's also more easily translatable, at least
as far as תוספות Tosafot is concerned, to issues that have nothing
to do with agriculture, right? Give the מעשר Maaser and, you know,
and it'll help your general success in business and in all types
of things. So that's interesting again to note what, you know, the
elimination of rain from the equation. The other thing I just will
point about about this תוספות Tosafot is what's the indication that this
is not a tannaic source, this issue about—well it's
all Aramaic—well no, but ריבית.
ribbit. ריבית. ribbit. ריבית. ribbit.
Right, ריבית, ribbit, the idea that ריבית ribbit was mentioned at all
and mentioned first, right? That when did the Jews start making money
from, you know, charging interest was really only in the Middle Ages.
So this clearly and there we don't have this in our ספרי.
Sifrei. And though some ראשוני אשכנז Rishonei Ashkenaz will claim that the
idea of מעשר כספים Maaser Kesafim is biblical or rabbinic, the overwhelming
consensus is that it's a מנהג. minhag. But it's a fascinating idea
which is taking something which was, you know, so much central to,
you know, our religious and social obligations, societal obligations in terms of
our, you know, in terms of our income and how that became
moot once A: we weren't living in Israel and B: our income
wasn't based on agriculture. So, you know, it's really like the taking
of this value and saying we're not prepared to give up this
value and finding a way to still hold onto it and transfer
it from this halachic or biblical מעשר Maaser of grain to this
idea of מעשר כספים. Maaser Kesafim. And but, you know, again, but
then it becomes also difficult with that sense about for some people:
well, if it's not actually הלכה, halacha, it's 10 percent, so do
I really have to do it? So, אגדות aggadot such as this
and about the consequences of the power of giving makes you rich,
not giving makes you poor and so on, are very powerful. Yes.
Is it just specifically a medieval period since you take it from
מעשר? Maaser?
So right, so that's a good question. The sense is, you know,
if you think about מעשר Maaser in general, the focus of the
מעשר Maaser in the פסוקים Pesukim is to give to God. Now
how do you give to God? So, you give to God by
giving to the לויים Leviyim or you give to God by bringing
to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. Every now and then, two
out of every six years you'll do something to the עניים, Aniyim,
but it doesn't focus on the עניים. Aniyim. The מעשר Maaser is
basically, you know,
conceptually it's giving it to God. Whereas for the ראשונים, Rishonim, the
emphasis was it's to give to the עניים. Aniyim. It was to
directly a way of framing what your צדקה tzedakah obligations were and
there are תשובות teshuvot written about can you direct some of your
מעשר כספים Maaser Kesafim money to religious purposes which are not specifically
about the poor. Like
ישיבות Yeshivot and שולן shuls and all those types of things. And
there's a debate about that. There's a debate about that. Yes.
Okay, Rabbi Leibtag, you wanted to know— I wanted to note that
I thought what was really powerful was the way his nephew spoke
to his uncle.
Yes, we're not done with that. Let's keep on going. Oh, you
mean it was a little חוצפהדיק? chutzpadik?
Well, I was going to say it serves as a very powerful
model for, okay, being respectful is one thing, but if you're engaged
in תורה Torah learning, you're allowed to engage with
challenges, right, right.
You still don't think it was a little חוצפהדיק? chutzpadik? Heck, if
I would have got to that פסוק, pasuk, who would have, I
wouldn't have needed you. Or הושעיה, Hoshaya, you know, רבי הושעיה, Rebbi
Hoshaya, הושעיה, Hoshaya, your רבי, Rebbi, I don't know.
So okay, this belongs in like...
Well, let's keep on going. Well, one person's enthusiasm is another person's
חוצפה, chutzpah, so let's keep on going just like this. Two, and
in addition, אשכחיה רבי יוחנן לינוקא דריש לקיש. ashkechei Rabbi Yochanan leyenuka
d'Reish Lakish. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan found ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish child,
דיתיב ואמר, deyatib ve'amar, was sitting and saying the following פסוק: pasuk:
אולת אדם תסלף דרכו, ivelet adam tesalef darko, the foolishness of a
man will pervert his path, ועל ה׳ יזעף לבו, ve'al Hashem yiza'af
libo, and on God he will direct his anger, you know, his
heart will be angry.
Years later, he's going to get
up to, you know, to משלי, Mishlei, maybe he didn't go in
order. יתיב רבי, yatib rebbi, maybe he realized, oh, I missed a
פסוק pasuk in מלאכי, Malachi, I gotta start from the other end
and work back maybe or something, I don't know. Anyway, יתיב רבי
יוחנן, yatib Rabbi Yochanan, so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was sitting וקמתמה,
vekamitama, he overheard this and he was astounded, he was thinking about
this. אמר, amar, he said, מי איכא מידי, mi ika midi, is
there anything דכתיבי בכתובים dechtivi bechtuvim that's written in the כתובים, Kesuvim,
in the later writings, דלא רמיזי באורייתא delo remizi be'orayta that isn't
already hinted to in the תורה? Torah? Because the תורה Torah is
the source of everything. אמר ליה, amar lei,
so he said back to him, אטו הא מי לא רמיזי, atu
ha mi lo remizi, are you telling me, meaning the kid is
answering back to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan before רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
sort of bested him by quoting a פסוק. pasuk. Here the kid
is the one coming up with the answer. Wait, this is hinted
to in the פסוקים. pesukim. הכתיב, hachtiv, the verse says: ויצא לבם
ויחרדו איש אל אחיו לאמר מה זאת עשה אלקים לנו, vayeitzei libam
vayechredu ish el achiv leimor mah zot asah Elokim lanu, right?
So here when the brothers are starting, you know, they're suffering the
consequences of selling יוסף, Yosef, they're saying what did God do to
us? They're blaming God about it. So also you see, you go
ahead and your misdeeds cause your own, you know, state of affairs,
but you wind up blaming God exactly like the פסוק pasuk in
משלי. Mishlei. So דל עיניה, dal einei, so he lifted up his
eyes. In other stories רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan has like super long
eyelashes that he needs people to lift up for him, but those
are very much Babylonian אגדתא. Agadata. Anyway, דל עיניה, dal einei, he
lifted up his eyes, וחזייה, vechazayei,
and he saw him, he looked at him. So and maybe he
was looking at him with not a pleasant look, like you know,
with a... so אתא אימיה, ata imei, his mother came, this is
רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan sister, אפיקתיה, afiktei, and got him out of
there. אמרה ליה, amrah lei, and she said to him, her son,
תא מקמיה, ta mikamei, go away from him, דלא ליעביד לך כדעבד
לאבוך, delo le'avid lach k'da'avad le'avuch, he shouldn't do to you like
he did to your father, because there's a story that רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan gave a look to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish died. So basically these go back to a series
of stories where rabbis give these, you know, evil looks to people
that they are not finding favor in their eyes and they drop
dead.
You remind him of his past, you remind him of his
past. רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Yeah.
Well, this is ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish kid.
I know, I understand, but like this is what he did to
the father.
Exactly. So the mother, רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan sister, ריש לקיש's Reish
Lakish widow, said to her son, you better get out of here
so he doesn't kill you.
He doesn't kill you like he killed your father. Okay. So alright,
so that was a pretty interesting end to that story. I don't
know what I get, what I do get from it is the
following, is that again, you know, the גמרא Gemara is once again
regularly shifting between the issues of rain and תורה, Torah, specifically also
תורה Torah in the context of the relationship of a רבי Rebbi
to a student. That's been a constant theme moving back and forth,
and I think the idea again is, is that you know, is
the relationship aspect, you know, God gives us the rain, it's God
communicating with us, God, you know, intimacy with us, and there's this
sort of רבי-student Rebbi model as well which sort of maps onto
that. So here you see, and maybe it's almost like in contrast,
and I think this is going to play out later, you know,
here you can annoy the... if you annoy the רבי, Rebbi, he
can look at you and drop dead, whereas God presumably, you know,
God's with everything that we've seen before about the rain, it has
not been that harsh and that fatal. You know, so I think
maybe in a way it's almost suggesting that God's relationship to us
is more compassionate than the one sometimes we actually assign here.
Or your uncle killed your father, you don't have to be polite
to him.
There you go.
Which is just the opposite.
In a respectful way, this kid might have some
baggage.
With your uncle.
His mother feels that he's acting inappropriately towards his uncle.
Aha, so you mean this helps us to understand what the חוצפה
chutzpah response was before. Yeah.
How do we know the boy in the story was ריש לקיש's
Reish Lakish son?
Well,
it says his son, ינוקא דריש לקיש. yenuka d'Reish Lakish. Okay, well
this one does.
They both did.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, yeah, I can interpret this completely differently. It could have been
a rhetorical question all
the
time.
Maybe there's more than that. Maybe. Maybe. Look, I also think here
that it's immediately in the context of like two things again about
the relationship. One is, you know, if you give, if you give
מעשר, ma'aser, God will give you all these blessings. And the other
thing is, and sometimes you, you know, like a kid will sometimes
just put all, display all of their anger and frustration on their
parents. So here you're a person, right, you've caused your own situation
and you blame it all on God. Okay? So, and so, you
know, but, but nevertheless, I think with all of this, you know,
God is not acting in a capricious or overly harsh way. In
a way God is promising blessing, you might blame God, but it
doesn't say God is going to react. And I think that that's
being implicitly contrasted to how, you know, rashly and fatally רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan reacted when he felt his honor was being challenged. So
to me, I see this as suggesting a strong contrast between these
two. Let's keep on reading. Okay, so it says like this.
Okay, ואמר רבי יוחנן, v'amar Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan also
says, מטר בשביל יחיד פרנסה בשביל רבים. matar bishvil yachid parnasa bishvil
rabbim. God will bring rain even for one person. One person deserves
rain, God will make it rain for that one person. But פרנסה,
parnasa, general sense of like sustenance, of well-being of the economy, you
know, more broad sustenance, that's only if the masses deserve it. מטר
בשביל יחיד דכתיב, matar bishvil yachid dechtiv, יפתח השם לך, yiftach Hashem
lecha, God should open for you in the singular,
את אוצרו הטוב לתת מטר ארצך, et otzaro hatov latet matar artzecha,
to give the rain of your land, singular. פרנסה בשביל רבים דכתיב,
parnasa bishvil rabbim dechtiv, הנני ממטיר לכם לחם מן השמים. hineni mamtir
lachem lechem min hashamayim. I am going to rain down for you,
you know, bread from the heavens. So לכם lachem is in the
plural. So it's not just the rain, it's more broadly פרנסה parnasa
and therefore that would only be for the masses. מתיבי, metivei, now
which again, that's quite fascinating given that this whole מסכת masechet is
about if it doesn't rain, then it's about a ציבור, tzibur, it's
a problem of the community and a communal fast. And here we're
sort of seeing that the rain might at least maybe the positive
aspects of the rain might be coming, maybe withholding the rain is
a communal issue, but the fact that it's raining, you know, might
even be for the sake of an individual. In a way as
I've mentioned, one theme that will be coming up is the יחידים
yechidim that pray when it stopped, initially even before the ציבור tzibur
prays and again, חוני המעגל, Choni HaMa'agel, right? So there is a
role of יחידים yechidim in the rain as well, and that will
be another theme. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
מתיבי, metivei, I ask you on this, רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר,
Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda omer, שלשה פרנסים טובים עמדו לישראל, shelosha parnasim
tovim amdu l'Yisrael, three great providers stood up for the Jewish people.
אלו הן, elu hein, and these are they: משה ואהרן ומרים. Moshe
ve'Aharon u'Miriam. וג' מתנות טובות נתנו על ידם, vegimel matanot tovot nitnu
al yadam, and three great gifts were given through them. ואלו הן,
ve'elu hein, באר וענן ומן, be'er ve'anan u'man, the well and the
cloud and the and the מן. man. באר בזכות מרים, be'er bizchut
Miriam, the well for, in the merit of מרים. Miriam. מרים Miriam
also very connected to water and the whole water and nurturing. Again,
we've had a discussion whether water and the rain is a, well
this is not the rain, but anyway is a male or female
image. But okay, here it's connected to מרים. Miriam. עמוד ענן בזכות
אהרן, amud anan bizchut Aharon, the cloud in the, in the honor
of אהרן. Aharon. ומן, uman, and you know, again, just to say
some type of a connection, you know, of course it's אהרן Aharon
who brings the ענן הקטורת. anan haketoret. We have קטרת ketoret in
this week's פרשה, parsha, you know, and that ענן, anan, that sense
of God's presence in the משכן, Mishkan, so maybe that's some of
the connection
there. ומן בזכות משה, u'man bizchut Moshe, and the מן man in
the merit of משה. Moshe. מתה מרים נסתלק הבאר, meta Miriam nistalek
habe'er, when מרים Miriam died the באר be'er disappeared, שנאמר ותמת שם
מרים וכתיב בתריה ולא היה מים לעדה, shene'emar vatamot sham Miriam uchsiv
batrey velo hayah mayim l'eida, so there was no water. So what's
the connection? The מרים, Miriam, on מרים's Miriam merit they had this
well that, that carried, that came around with them. רש"י Rashi says
it was a rock that water came out of because we know
water's coming out of rocks a lot in the תורה. Torah. And
when מרים Miriam died, so it was no longer there and that's
why they thirsted. וחזרה בזכות שניהם, vechazra bizchut shneihem, and in the
merit of the two of them it came back. רש"י Rashi says
how do you know it came back in the merit of the
two of them? Because God says to משה Moshe and אהרן: Aharon:
go and speak to the rock and it'll bring out the water.
So that's the two of them brought back the, the water. מת
אהרן נסתלקו ענני הכבוד, met Aharon nistalku ananei hakavod, אהרן Aharon died,
the heavenly clouds disappeared, שנאמר וישמע הכנעני מלך ערד, shene'emar vayishma HaKena'ani
Melech Arad, the Canaanite the king of Arad heard, והוא יושב הנגב,
v'hu yoshev hanagev, right, ובבוא ישראל, uvavo Yisrael, and the Israel was
coming and whatever and he went to war against them. So מה
שמועה שמע? mah shemu'ah shama? What, what did he hear? So the
simple sense of the פסוק pasuk is that he heard that ישראל
Yisrael was passing by. But the גמרא Gemara says what did he
hear? He heard what it said about in the previous פרק. perek.
שמע שמת אהרן ונסתלקו ענני הכבוד, shama shemet Aharon venistalku ananei hakavod,
he heard that אהרן Aharon died and the heavenly clouds had departed
and they were now exposed and not protected, וכסבור נתנה לו רשות
להלחם בישראל, ukesavur nitnu lo reshut lehilachem b'Yisrael, he has permission to
go to war against Israel. He's now to go to war against
Israel, שזה היינו דכתיב Dechsiv. *shezeh haynu dechsiv*, that's what it says,
ויראו כל העדה כי גוע אהרן *vayiru kol ha'eda ki gava Aharon*,
the whole nation saw that אהרן *Aharon* had died, expired. אמר רבי
Rebbe אבהו *Amar Rabi Abbahu*, אל תקרי ויראו *al tikrei vayiru*, do
not say they saw, אלא וייראו *ela vayyere'u*, they were, they appeared,
they were exposed, they were visible, they became visible. כדריש לקיש *Kedreish
Lakish*, like ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish*, דאמר ריש לקיש D'amar
Reish Lakish. *da'amar Reish Lakish*, כי משמש בארבע לשונות *ki meshamesh be'arba
leshonot*, כי *ki* has four meanings: אי דילמא אלא דהא *ei dilma
ela deha*. We had this earlier, I'm not going to totally unpack
this right here. This, we had this from Rosh Hashanah. Anyway, אי
*ei* if, דילמא *dilma* lest, אלא *ela* rather, and דהא *deha* that
or because. So here, treating וייראו *vayyere'u*, they were, they became visible
and exposed, כי גוע אהרן *ki gava Aharon*, because אהרן *Aharon* had
died. Not they saw that אהרן *Aharon* had died, they became visible
because אהרן *Aharon* had died. So the clouds went away when אהרן
*Aharon* died. חזרו שניהם
בזכות משה *Chazru
sheneihem bizchut Moshe*, then we, but משה *Moshe* brought both of them
back.
I don't know how we know that. מית משה *Met Moshe*, and
then when משה *Moshe* died, נסתלקו כולם *nistalku kulam*, then they all
disappeared. שנאמר she'ne'emar *Shene'emar*, as the verse says, ואכחיד שלשת הרועים בירח
אחד *va'achchid shloshet haro'im beyerach echad*, I will destroy the three shepherds
in one month. So where were the three shepherds? It must have
been משה *Moshe*, אהרן *Aharon*, and מרים *Miriam*, the three leaders. But
בירח אחד *beyerach echad*, did they really all die in one month?
והלא מרים מתה בניסן *Vahalo Miriam meta beNisan*, מרים *Miriam* died in
ניסן *Nisan* because it says before the story of מרים *Miriam*, it
says חודש הראשון *chodesh harishon*, ואהרן באב *veAharon beAv*, and אהרן *Aharon*
died in אב *Av*, ומשה באדר *uMoshe beAdar*. If you look in
the פסוקים pesukim *psukim* you'll see that. So what does it mean
all in one month? אלא מלמד שנתבטלו ג' מתנות טובות שניתנו על
ידם *ela melamed shenisbatlu gimmel matanot tovot shenitnu al yadam*, all three
gifts were, you know, ceased in one month. So that's how you
know indirectly that משה *Moshe* brought them back, because if they all
disappeared at once, it must have been that they returned for the
sake of משה *Moshe* and now משה *Moshe* died, they all disappeared.
ונסתלקו כולם בירח אחד *venistalku kulam beyerach echad*, and they all disappeared.
Now that was all fascinating. Why is it relevant to us? It's
relevant to us because of the following. אלמא אשכחן פרנסא בשביל יחיד
*alma ashkechan parnasa bishvil yachid*. So you see one person, just משה
*Moshe*, or just משה *Moshe*, just אהרן *Aharon*, just מרים *Miriam*, they
brought פרנסא *parnasa*. משה *Moshe* brought the מן *man*. So it wasn't
just פרנסא *parnasa* because of the רבים *rabim*. So there's obviously an
answer here. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no. שאני משה כיון דלרבים
הוא בעי כרבים דמי *shani Moshe kivan delarabim hu ba'ei kerabim dami*.
משה *Moshe* is different. Since he's needed for the masses, you know,
obviously he's a leader, so he's like the masses. So it's coming
on his merit. It can come for the merit of one person
if that person is in a position of leadership like משה *Moshe*.
But in general, for there to be general, you know, success in
the economy, that's coming as a result of that the masses deserve
it. As opposed to rain, that could come for just the sake
of one person. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, רב הונא בר
מנוח ורב שמואל בר אידי ורב חייא מוסתניא *Rav Huna bar Manoach
veRav Shmuel bar Idi veRav Chiyya miVastanya*. Now we have this פסוק
pasuk. *pasuk* of ואכחיד שלשת הרועים *va'achchid shloshet haro'im*. We're going to
repeat a theme that we just introduced earlier with רבי Rebbe יוחנן
*Rabi Yochanan*. So רב הונא בר מנוח ורב שמואל בר אידי ורב
חייא מוסתניא *Rav Huna bar Manoach veRav Shmuel bar Idi veRav Chiyya
miVastanya* הוו שכיחי קמיה דרבא *havu shechichi kamei deRava*.
So they used to be in front of רבא *Rava*. They were
רבא *Rava*'s תלמידים *talmidim* and they would learn from רבא *Rava*. כי
נח נפשיה דרבא *ki nach nafshei deRava*, now רבא *Rava* passed away.
אתו לקמיה דרב פפא *atu lekamei deRav Papa*. All right, so they
went to learn from רב פפא Rav Papa, *Rav Papa*. כל אימת
דהוה אמר להו שמעתא *kol eimat dehavah amar lehu shamata*, every time
רב פפא Rav Papa. *Rav Papa* would say over a סוגיא *sugya*,
would say over a teaching, ולא הוה מסתברא להו *velo havah mistabra
lehu*, and it did not make so much sense to them, like
he wasn't saying it over so sharply or so clearly, הוו מרמזי
אהדדי *havu meramzi ahadadi*. They would signal one another that oh god,
like, you know, whatever they'd say, they'd, you know, say something to
indicate like this ain't like it used to be with רבא *Rava*.
If רבא *Rava* was here, we would know what was going on.
So חלש דעתיה *chalash datei*. You can totally see this. חלש דעתיה
*chalash datei* דרב פפא *deRav Papa*. רב פפא Rav Papa. *Rav Papa*
became very despondent. He became, he said, like, he felt terrible, like,
you know, embarrassed every day that he's not as smart as רבא
*Rava* or not as good of a teacher. So אקרויה בחלמיה *akruyei
bechalmei*, so they,
whoever they is up in heaven, they read to רב פפא Rav
Papa *Rav Papa* the following verse in his dream: ואכחיד שלשת הרועים
*va'achchid shloshet haro'im*,
I will destroy the three shepherds. He had these three students. So
oh, it'll make you feel better, רב פפא Rav Papa *Rav Papa*,
don't worry, we'll just get rid of them. למחר *lemachar*, the next
morning, כי הוו מפטרי מיניה *ki havu mifteri minei*, when they took
their leave from him at the end of the שיעור *shiur*, אמר
להו *amar lehu*, לזיל רבנן בשלמא *leizil rabanan beshalma*, the rabbis should
go in peace, which is basically like saying, you know, goodbye, I'm
not going to be seeing you anymore. So which is pretty sad
story. I mean, it's not like he tries to pray in their
defense, it's not like he whatever, it's like he was happy with
that result or maybe he felt he couldn't do anything about it.
But anyway, the point being that they're now, you know, he's maybe
not to blame, he didn't ask for it, but nevertheless, he seems
a little bit, a little bit insensitive to the result. But once
again, we have this idea that the student, the relationship of the
students and the rabbi, when not ideal, leads to very fatal and
drastic results. result as a and this is in direct contrast to
the way I'm reading this to the fact for just one person
God to bring rain. You know, God is the much more compassionate
father parent or whatever teacher than human beings. Human beings, you have,
you know, you annoy them and they give you a look or
whatever it is and it could be drastic. You know, God just
for one person will bring rain. That's what I sort of see
as the implicit contrast.
But you see Rabbis don't die.
We never hear exactly what happened.
And the note here says he blessed the Rabbis to protect them
from the result.
Yeah, that to me feels a little apologetic. Okay. Extremely apologetic. Yeah.
It seems a little apologetic. And let's keep on reading. Okay. What?
I know. Let's keep on reading. Okay. So רב שימי בר אשי,
Rav Shimi bar Ashi so another story that somewhat reinforces this but
has a little be more preventative. רב שימי בר אשי הוי שכיח
קמיה דרב פפא. Rav Shimi bar Ashi havai shechiach kamei deRav Papa.
He used to be in front of רב פפא, Rav Papa learn
from רב פפא. Rav Papa הוי מקשי ליה טובא. Havai makshi lei
tuvei. And he would ask a lot of good קשיות kashyas against
רב פפא. So יומא חד חזיה דנפל אפיה. yoma chad chazyei denafal
apei. One day רב שימי Shimi. בר אשי saw רב פפא like,
you know, fall on his face. Like he had so many questions,
he just put his head down on the table. Wait, wait, wait.
You know, you're overwhelming me. Hold on. Like he saw him fall
on his face. שמע דאמר. Shama d'amar. And then he overheard רב
פפא saying.
רחמנא ליצלן מכיסופא דשימי. Rachmana litzlan mikisufa deShimi. God should save us
from the embarrassment of שימי. Shimi So שימי Shimi was embarrassing him
every day with such good questions. Now we already know exactly the
idea of what it means for God to save רב פפא from
embarrassment. So שמע. shama. So what did he do? So קיבל עליה
שתיקותא. kibeil alei shitikusa. So שימי decided from that point on I'm
not asking any questions. I'm just going to keep quiet. Rather not
ask my questions and not have to suffer what it means to
protect רב פפא from his embarrassment. ולא אקשי ליה. V'lo akshi lei.
And he didn't ask him anymore. Okay, so again, you know, pretty
harsh in terms of that relationship or in terms of the sort
of tiptoeing around that relationship.
ואפרשי שקי, Va'afrei shaki, back to our major theme. But again, the
constant shifting back and forth between rain and רבי and student is
I see just, you know, is consistent here and constant. ואפרשי שקי
סבר. Va'afrei shaki savar. And even ריש לקיש Reish Lakish holds. שתיקותא
מטר בשביל יחיד. Shitikusa matar bishvil yachid.
That rain can come even for an individual. דאמר ריש לקיש. For
ריש לקיש says. מניין למטר בשביל יחיד. Minayin lematar bishvil yachid.
How do you know rain comes for an individual? דכתיב. The verse
says. שאלו מה' מטר בעת מלקוש. Sha'alu meHashem matar b'eis malkosh.
Ask from God for rain at the time of the מלקוש, malkosh,
late rain. ה' עושה חזיזים. Hashem oseh chazizim.
God makes חזיזים. chazizim. We'll see how the גמרא explains that. Some
English have that as like lightnings. ומטר גשם יתן. U'matar geshem yitein.
And rain and the rain whatever God will give. יתן להם. Yitein
lahem. Will give to them. לאיש עשב בשדה. L'ish eisev basadeh. To
each
person עשב eisev in the field. So it's לאיש, l'ish, even for
one person. יכול לכל. Yachol lakol. Maybe God will only bring rain
for everyone. If everyone needs it or deserves it. תלמוד לומר לאיש.
Talmud lomar l'ish. Even for one person. ותניא, Vetanya, we learn a
ברייתא. braitisa. אי לאיש יכול לכל שדותיו. I l'ish yachol lechol sadosav.
Maybe all his fields. Like maybe, you know, as long as we're
bringing rain for one person, we're not going to be more, you
know, sort of micro than that. And all of the fields will
be rained on. No? תלמוד לומר שדה. Talmud lomar sadeh. If one
field needs it and one field doesn't, it'll only rain on the
field that needs it. אי שדה יכול לכל השדה. I sadeh yachol
lechol hasadeh. Maybe the whole field? תלמוד לומר עשב. Talmud lomar eisev.
Even on one piece of grass. So the rain could be very
precise. So, you know, I do think that what this is reflecting
is the reality as we experience it, which is, you know, sometimes
it rains very briefly, sometimes it rains in one spot and not
another spot, sometimes it rains and it stops raining. So again, if
you're interpreting that theologically, you're saying, well, God can bring rain exactly
whom and when and where it's exactly needed.
Okay, so כי הא דרב דניאל בר קטינא. ki ha deRav Daniel
bar Katina. Like this of רב דניאל בר קטינא. Rav Daniel bar
Katina. דהוי ליה ההיא גינותא. Dehavai lei hahi ginosai. He had a
garden. כל
יומא הוי אזיל סייר לה. Kol yoma havai azil sayer lah. Every
day he would go and he would inspect it. אמר האי משרא
בעי מיא. Amar hai mishra ba'ei maya. This bed requires water, this
furrow needs water. והאי משרא לא בעי מיא. Veha mishra lo ba'ei
maya. And this one doesn't need water. ואתי מטרא דקמשקי כל היכא
דמיבעי ליה. Ve'asai mitra dekamashki kol heicha de'miba'ei lei. And then the
rain would come and it would water exactly the places that needed
the water and not the places that didn't. מיבעי ליה מיא. Miba'ei
lei maya. Which again, fascinating about this is that sort of sense
of confidence. Like he can say this yes and this no, it
seems like he's almost expecting God to then listen and follow suit.
Okay, now the גמרא interprets the פסוק. מאי ה' עושה חזיזים? Mai
Hashem oseh chazizim? God makes חזיזים. chazizim. אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא.
Amar Rabbi Yose b'Rebbi Chanina. מלמד שכל צדיק וצדיק הקדוש ברוך הוא
עושה לו חזיז בפני עצמו. Melameid shekol tzaddik vetzaddik Hakadosh Baruch Hu
oseh lo chaziz bifnei atzmo. So again here the sense of God,
you know, not the rain is not just this sort of macro
way of God interacting with the world. You know, this whole question
of course, you know, how does an infinite regard God relate to
like a finite human being and the finite world. So for some
people it's So for some people it's an easier answer if you
think about that there's not in terms of like what we call
השגחה פרטית *hashgacha pratis*, not in terms of like, well, God doesn't
micromanage every detail, maybe like the broad strokes. So
again what this גמרא *Gemara* is insisting is no again and again
sort of thinking about the religious significance that the rain is indicating
not just God's general interaction with us but at you know at
very much at the individual level
signifying God's relationship to us. So so this is again the theme
here that for every צדיק וצדיק *tzadik v'tzadik* God makes an individual
חזיז *chaziz*. So okay what's the חזיז *chaziz*? So that's the plural
but מה חזיזין *mai chazizim* what are these חזיזין *chazizim*? So אמר
רב יהודה *amar Rav Yehuda* פורחת *porachas* it's פורחות *porchos*. So what's
that? So אמר רבי יוחנן *amar Rabbi Yochanan* סימן למטרא פורחות *siman
l'matara porchos* a sign that it's going to rain are these פורחות
*porchos*. מאי פורחות *mai porchos* what are the פורחות *porchos*? אמר רב
פפא *amar Rav Pappa* עיבא קלישא תותי עיבא סמיכתא *eiva klisha tusei
eiva smikta* a thin cloud underneath a thick dark heavy cloud. So
if you have a little thin cloud you know coming underneath it
that's a sign that there will be a lot of rain or
good rain I guess. אמר רב יהודה *amar Rav Yehuda* נהילה מקמי
מטרא אתי מטרא *nehila mikmi matra ati matra*. If these small clouds
come before the rain then the rain will come or then it'll
be a good rain. בתר מטרא פסיק מטרא *basar matra pasik matra*
if it comes after the
rain then the rain will stop
immediately you know very soon or immediately after and it won't resume.
Now מקמי מטרא אתי מטרא *mikmi matra ati matra* the idea that
if you see these little clouds before the rain the rain will
come out you know well וסימנך מכלתא *v'simanch machulta* like a sieve
like if you're using a sieve first comes out the depending on
the sieve I guess first comes out like the fine stuff
and then the
and then comes out wait did I skip a line? No? Okay
okay like a sieve first comes out like
the one minute one minute where is the one moment one moment.
Oh no no I misread I forgot to interpret the word. אמר
רב יהודה *amar Rav Yehuda* going back a few lines when רב
יהודה *Rav Yehuda* says נהילה *nehila* so נהילה *nehila* means a drizzle
like a thin rain. So he said now he's no longer about
the cloud. So אמר רב יהודה נהילה *amar Rav Yehuda nehila* thin
rain is how he's reading the a drizzle מקמי מטרא אתי מטרא
*mikmi matra ati matra* before the rain means that the rain will
come out will come well. בתר מטרא *basar matra* thin rain after
the rain after the heavy rain פסיק מטרא *pasik matra* will mean
the rain ends. Now מקמי מטרא אתי מטרא וסימנך מכלתא *mikmi matra
ati matra v'simanch machulta* like a sieve so first like this sometimes
the way whatever the types of way they sieved they sifted is
like the thin chaff would come out and then the heavy stuff
would come afterwards
at least that's what רש״י *Rashi* says. בתר מטרא פסיק מטרא *basar
matra pasik matra* a drizzle after the rain means the rain will
cease וסימנך חריא דעזי *v'simanch charya d'izei*
the excrement of goats apparently it comes out heavy and then if
it comes out in small it's like drizzles or whatever small then
it stops. Okay anyway it's a drizzle and the drizzle coming at
the right time is a sign that the rain will come. עולא
איקלע לבבל *Ulla ikla l'Bavel*. Now עולא *Ulla* came to בבל Bavel.
*Bavel*. חזא פורחות *chaza porchos* he saw these פורחות *porchos* either these
thin clouds or this thin rain. אמר להו *amar lehu* he said
to the people around him פנו מאני דהשתא אתי מטרא *pnu manei
de'hashta ati matra* get clear out the vessels you know take all
the stuff indoors it's about to come down like a you know
a heavy rain is about to come. ולסוף לא אתי מטרא *u'lesof
lo ati matra* and in the end no rain came even though
there were these thin clouds or this drizzle. אמר *amar* he said
כי היכי דמשקרי בבלאי הכי משקרי מטראי *ke'eichi de'meshakrei Bavla'ei hachi meshakrei
matra'ei*. Oh you see the same way Babylonians are
liars their rain is a liar. So so we have all these
signs like going back to the גמרא *Gemara* before about making promises
in public about giving צדקה *tzedakah* not fulfilling them you have all
the signs that rain will come and rain doesn't come and that
somehow is a reflection of the people of the place.
So again so the theme this type of metaphysical correspondence
or mispredicting the weather is already an ancient tradition
or rather to blame the fault on the people than on his
own mispredictions. Okay. עולא איקלע לבבל *Ulla ikla l'Bavel* עולא *Ulla* came
to בבל Bavel *Bavel*. חזי מלא צנא דתמרי *chazi mala tana d'tamrei*.
He saw a basket filled with dates בזוזא *b'zuza* for just a
זוז *zuz* a full basket of dates for a זוז *zuz*. What
a bargain! אמר *amar* he said מלא צנא דדובשא בזוזא *mala tana
d'duvsha b'zuza* you have a basket full of honey you know dates
are like they made honey out of them it's very sweet for
just a זוז *zuz* I mean there's so much plenty here there's
so much you know good food for for cheap. ובבלאי לא עסקי
באורייתא *u'Bavla'ei lo askei b'Oraisa*? How could it be that the Babylonians
don't involve themselves more in תורה Torah! *Torah* you know they have
such easy living. ולסוף בליליא צערוהו *u'lesof b'leilya tza'aru'hu* and at the
night it caused him pain like he ate a whole basket worth
so so he had you know so he had some stomach problems
he had some diarrhea. אמר *amar* he said מלא צנא דסכינא בזוזא
*mala tana d'sachina b'zuza*. Oh my god you have a basket filled
with knives for a זוז *zuz*. with with like danger in in
for a זוז, ובבלאי עסקי באורייתא, u'bavlai aski b'oreisa, and even so
the Babylonians were able to learn תורה! Torah, So now he realized
that this stuff wasn't necessarily a blessing, like so maybe it could,
you know, cause you all if you overeat it causes you all
these problems. So the fact that they're still able to learn תורה,
Torah you know, that's a wonderful thing. Anyway, it is interesting his
negative approach towards the the Babylonians especially thinking how it's you know
the תלמוד בבלי, Talmud Bavli, you know, and where certainly from the
בבלי Bavli's perspective the Babylonians learned תורה Torah, better than those in
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. But his general perception that maybe it's not
just a question of the quality of the תורה, Torah. maybe it's
a question of their dedication to the תורה. Torah Maybe he felt
that they weren't dedicated enough especially given the economy was better in
בבל. They had it better financially in בבל and as we know
sometimes a life of privation actually leads to more self-sacrifice and dedication.
When it's a little bit too easy maybe it does take you
astray a little bit and anyway that seems to be a little
what's going on here. Yes.
And an overarching sort of theme here, interleaving of rain and תורה
Torah study. Yes. Both are nuanced. Sometimes rain is good, sometimes it's
bad. That's true. It depends on the place, it depends on the
person, it depends on the כוונה. kavana. So too תורה Torah learning
depends on the relationship between the רבי and the student, the בנחת,
b'nachat, the annoying, you know, sometimes it's a blessing, sometimes it's an
irritant.
So you're saying it's here even just the sense of the of
like of the dates themselves. Is this a positive or a negative?
Right, you know, תורה study is like rain with all of its
powerful imagery.
That's a nice point.
The same nuances that apply to one apply to the other.
Very nice. Okay, now we get back to some
more I don't know scientific quote-unquote analysis of rain. Of the water
cycle, exactly. Okay. תנו רבנן ברייתא. Tanu Rabbanan Beraisa. תניא. Tanya. רבי
אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, כל עולם כולו ממי אוקיינוס הוא שותה.
kol olam kulo m'mei Okeinos hu shoteh. The whole world drinks from
the waters of the אוקיינוס Okeinos which is I don't know say
is that identified as the Atlantic what do they say the אוקיינוס?
Okeinos? The ocean. Oh I guess אוקיינוס, Okeinos, ocean, right. אוקיינוס. Okeinos.
אוקיינוס. Okeinos. What does that mean in modern Hebrew? Just ocean in
general? Okay. You don't say ים, yam, ים yam is like a
sea. So how do you say the Atlantic?
אוקיינוס. Okeinos. So it means ocean. Okay. All right. So ממי אוקיינוס,
m'mei Okeinos, from the from the ocean, which basically means it's the
he understood the idea of the water cycle, you know, the evaporation
leads to go to the clouds and it rains and it all
eventually feeds back and it all comes from the waters of the
ocean. שנאמר she'ne'emar as the verse says, ואד יעלה מן הארץ והשקה
את כל פני האדמה, v'eid ya'aleh min ha'aretz v'hishka kol p'nei ha'adama,
that the cloud rises from the ground and it waters all of
all of the earth. So the rain comes from ultimately starts from
the water that's on the ocean and it rises up and then
it falls back down.
אמר לו רבי יהושע, amar lo Rabbi Yehoshua, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
said to him, ולא ממי אוקיינוס מלוחין הן? v'lo m'mei Okeinos meluchin
hein? What do you mean, ocean water is salty and the rain
water isn't salty? אמר לו, amar lo,
ממתקין בעבים. mematkin b'avim. They get sweetened or מתמתקין בעבים. mitmatkin b'avim.
They get sweetened in the clouds. Actually what happens is they evaporate
and they leave the salt behind, right? Isn't that how they're not
salty? Yeah. Okay, fine. Okay. But anyway, he's basically got the water
cycle down. So רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, כל עולם כולו
ממים עליונים הוא שותה. kol olam kulo m'mayim elyonim hu shoteh. No,
it all comes from the waters that are above, right, you know,
because the רקיע rakia separates from the waters above and the waters
below, all the water ultimately comes from the water stored up in
heaven. שנאמר she'ne'emar as the verse says, למטר השמים תשתה מים, l'matar
hashamayim tishteh mayim, from the from the rain of the heavens you
will drink water. אלא מה אני מקיים ואד יעלה מן הארץ? ela
mah ani mekayem b'eid ya'aleh min ha'aretz? So what does it mean
that cloud rises up, which sounds like the water's coming from the
earth? מלמד שהעננים מתגברים ועולים לרקיע. melamed she'ananim mitgavrin v'olin l'rakia. The
clouds sort of get strengthened and rise up to the heavens, ופותחין
פיהם כנוד, u'potechin pihem k'nod, and they open up their mouths like
a like a like a waterskin, like a canteen, ומקבלין מי מטר,
u'mekablin m'mei matar, and they get filled up so the heavens is
the you know is the gas station, is the filling station. So
they don't get the water from the ground, they rise up, they
get filled with water from the heavens and then they bring it
down.
Okay. שנאמר she'ne'emar as the verse says, יזקו מטר לאדו, yazoku matar
l'eido, pour he will pour out rain to his cloud, ומנוקבות
הן ככברה u'menuvavos hein k'kivara and they are like they have holes
in them like a sieve, ובאות ומחשיבות מים על גבי קרקע, u'va'os
u'machashvos mayim al gabei karka, and they come and they rain down
water on the land, שנאמר חשרת מים עבי שחקים, chashras mayim avrei
shechakim, the sort of pouring out of water from the clouds of
the heavens. So ואין בין טיפה לטיפה אלא כמלא נימא, v'ein bein
tipa l'tipa ela kemlo nima, and between one drop and the next
drop there's only like a hairbreadth. So I don't know exactly how
that's relevant but I guess they've got a lot of holes but
basically it gets filled up above and then they pour out through
the sieve in the cloud.
ללמדך l'lamedcha and all of this teaches you, not exactly clear how
it teaches As he says the next פסוקים teach you שגדול יום
הגשמים כיום שנבראו בו שמים וארץ, she-gadol yom ha-geshamim k'yom she-nivreu bo
shamayim va-aretz, going back to an earlier theme שנאמר עושה גדולות ואין
חקר, she-ne'emar ose gadolot ve-ein cheker, God does wonders without a comprehension,
וכתיב הנותן מטר פני הארץ, ve-chtiv ha-noten matar p'nei ha-aretz, gives rain
on the land, וכתיב עליו הלא ידעת אם לא שמעת אלהי עולם
ה׳ אין חקר לתבונתו. ve-chtiv alav halo yadata im lo shamata elohei
olam Hashem ein cheker litvunato. Okay, so there's no comprehending God's wisdom,
understanding. Anyway, this is all terribly miraculous. So again, it's interesting, right?
Because for him to appreciate the sort of miraculous
nature of the rain means to interpret it in this very non-natural
way. Right? So this one who's saying the clouds go up, get
filled with the rains above the heaven and bring it down, and
look, it's like מעשה בראשית, ma'aseh bereishit, whereas the other one did
not make the comparison to מעשה בראשית. ma'aseh bereishit. Also this very
much evokes the idea that in מעשה בראשית ma'aseh bereishit it separates
the water, you know, the רקיע rakiya is supposed to separate the
water above and the water below. So this is going back to
that type of a cosmology, getting the water from above the רקיע
rakiya and bringing it back down. Okay, so we will have see
more of this tomorrow.